Finding Aid for William Warner Bishop Papers 1891-1955
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
William Warner Bishop Papers 1891-1955
Bishop, William Warner, 1871-1955.
Internationally recognized librarian; director of the University of Michigan Library. Correspondence and subject files relating to professional activities.
85496 Aa/2, Ac
25 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The bulk of the collection was transferred from the Graduate Library of the University of Michigan in 1975. Donor number 1278. Smaller additions were received from the Bishop family.
The collection is open for research.
Bishop's student notebooks from philosophy courses taught by John Dewey (Box 24) are also available on microfilm.
William Warner Bishop was librarian of the University of Michigan from 1915 until his retirement in 1941. After graduating from the University of Michigan (M.A. 1893), Bishop taught Greek at Missouri Wesleyan College (1893-1894) and then became an instructor in New Testament Greek and assistant librarian at Garrett Biblical Institute in Evanston, Illinois. He was a fellow at the American School for Classical Studies in Rome in 1898-1899. On his return to the United States he became librarian and instructor in Latin at the Polytechnic Institute of Brooklyn, New York, where he served from 1899 to 1902. Two years as head cataloger at Princeton University preceded his appointment as reference librarian at the Library of Congress in 1904. Bishop remained at the Library of Congress serving from 1907 to 1915 as superintendent of the reading room. In 1915, he was appointed librarian at the University of Michigan, succeeding Theodore Wesley Koch.
As librarian, Bishop was greatly responsible for the growth of the collection, the development and training of the staff, and the contacts established with European bookdealers and librarians. One of Bishop's most significant contributions was the establishment under his leadership of a department of library science to train individuals in bibliographical and other library-related skills.
Bishop was highly respected within his profession. He served as consultant on many of the library projects sponsored by the Carnegie Corporation; and he was chairman of the Advisory Group on College Libraries which assisted in building up the book collections of many college libraries in the United States and Canada. In no area of library work did he make a greater contribution than in international relations. In 1928 Bishop was invited by the Carnegie Endowment for International Peace to head the American group of librarians and others in initiating the reorganization of the Vatican Library. In addition, he served as president of the International Federation of Library Associations from 1931 to 1936; and as chairman of the International Relations Committee of the American Library Association, he promoted exchanges of library personnel and was instrumental in bringing many foreign librarians to this country and in providing library experience abroad for selected American librarians.
Bishop died February 19, 1955.
The collection has been arranged into eight series:
Correspondence -- Boxes 1-3
Articles, Lectures, and Addresses -- Boxes 4-5
American Library Association -- Boxes 6-15
Carnegie Corporation of New York; Topical Files -- Boxes 16-27
Visual Materials -- Box 27
Student Notebooks -- Boxes 28-30
Miscellaneous and Personal -- Boxes 30-31
The Bishop papers consist of personal and professional files documenting William Warner Bishop's activities apart from his work as librarian at the University of Michigan. The librarian's files were separately received and continue to be maintained as part of the records of the University of Michigan Library.
Subjects:
American Library Association.; Bishop, William Warner, 1871-1955.; Carnegie Corporation of New York. Advisory Group on College Libraries.; Carnegie Endowment for International Peace.; Libraries--United States.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Library.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Hiera Monē Iōannou tou Theologou Patmou.; Librarians.; Libraries.; Monasteries--Greece--Patmos.; Mussolini, Benito, 1883-1945.; Patmos (Greece); Quadrangle Club (University of Michigan); University of Michigan. Dept. of Library Science.; William L. Clements Library.
Genre/Form:
Diaries.; Photographs.
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series includes files letters, personal and professional, received and sent, in the period of 1891-1952. This series also includes letterbooks of copies of outgoing letters written while Bishop was at the Library of Congress as the Superintendent of the Reading Room. The dates of the letterbooks are 1907 to 1915.
  - Filed letters
    - 1891-1925 (Box 1)
    - 1925-1940 (Box 2)
    - 1940-1952 (Box 3)
  - Letterbooks
    (copies of outgoing correspondence of WWB as superintendent of the reading room of the Library of Congress)
    - 1907-1908 (Box 3)
    - 1908-1914 (Box 3)
    - 1909-1915 (Box 3)
- Articles, lectures, addresses
  The Articles, Lectures, and Addresses series consists of writings and speeches primarily in the period following Bishop's coming to the University of Michigan. The files in this series are dated 1919-1951.
  - Articles 1919-1951 (Box 4)
  - Lectures and addresses 1919-1943 (Box 5)
- American Library Association
  American Library Association is a series consisting of general correspondence, committee files, and other subject files detailing Bishop's lifelong association with the ALA. This series includes extensive documentation of his work with the Committee on International Relations and the Committee on Resources.
  - General Correspondence files
    - 1907-1918 (Box 5)
    - 1919-1933 (Box 6)
  - Executive Officers and administration
    - President 1920-1932 (Box 6)
    - Secretary 1918-1925/26 (Box 6)
    - Secretary 1926/27-1929/30 (Box 7)
    - Conference files 1919 (Box 7)
    - Mid-Winter Meeting 1916, 1919 (Box 7)
    - Post-Conference trip 1926-1927 (Box 7)
    - Council 1907, 1921-1924 (Box 7)
    - Council summaries (Box 7)
    - Nominations 1916 (Box 7)
    - Nominating Committee 1919 (Box 7)
    - Executive Board 1918-1932 (Box 7)
    - Assistant Secretary 1920-1932 (Box 8)
    - Treasurer 1924-1925 (Box 8)
    - Trustees Section 1922 (Box 8)
  - Topical Files (mainly committees)
    - Board of Education for Librarianship 1924-1944 (Box 8)
    - Booklist 1920-1929 (Box 8)
    - Current Budget 1926-1927 (Box 8)
    - California-ALA (Box 8)
    - College and Reference Section 1906-1908, 1917-1918, 1921-1925 (Box 8)
    - College and University Librarians 1926-1927 (Box 8)
    - Committees 1918-1921 (Box 9)
    - Committee of Eleven 1918-1919 (Box 9)
    - Committee of Five 1919, 1919-1925 (Box 9)
    - Committee of Twenty-five 1922-1923 (Box 9)
    - Committee on ALA Activities 1929-1932 (Box 9)
    - Committee on Bibliography 1924-1933 (Box 9)
    - Committee on Bookbinding 1908, 1924-1925 (Box 9)
    - Committee on Bookbuying 1922 (Box 9)
    - Committee on Books for Foreign Countries 1922-1929 (Box 9)
    - Committee on the Catalogue General of the Bibliotheque Nationale 1928-1929 (Box 9)
    - Committee on the Classification of Personnel 1924-1928 (Box 9)
    - Committee on Code of Ethics 1938-1939 (Box 9)
    - Catalog section 1907, 1917, 1922-1925 (Box 9)
    - Committee on Catalog Code Revision 1932-1938 (Box 9)
    - Committee on Cataloging 1922-1924 (Box 9)
    - Committee on Cataloging and Classification 1937-1939 (Box 9)
    - Committee on Catalog Rules 1920 (Box 9)
    - Committee on Committees 1922-1923, 1930-1935 (Box 9)
    - Committee on Cooperative Cataloging 1931-1933 (Box 9)
    - Committee on Devastated Libraries 1940-1941 (Box 9)
    - Committee on Evans Bibliography 1923-1925 (Box 9)
    - Committee on Enlarged Program 1919-1921 (Box 9)
    - Committee on Federal and State Relations 1931-1932 (Box 9)
    - Committee on Federal Relations 1937-1939 (Box 9)
    - Committee on Fiftieth Anniversary 1924-1927 (Box 9)
    - Committee on Importations 1919-1920 (Box 9)
    - Committee on International Bibliography 1919-1920, 1927-1928 (Box 9)
    - Committee on International Relations 1917-1945 (Box 10)
    - Committee on International Relations (Box 11)
      (dates vary)
    - Committee on Intellectual Cooperation 1926-1928 (Box 11)
    - Committee on Library Administration 1921-1922 (Box 11)
    - Committee on Library Cooperation 1920-1924 (Box 11)
    - Committee on Library Cooperation with Hispanic Peoples 1928-1929 (Box 11)
    - Committee on Library Radio Broadcasting 1929-1930 (Box 11)
    - Committee on Library Training 1920-1924 (Box 11)
    - Committee on Local Managements 1921-1922 (Box 11)
    - Membership Committee 1923-1924 (Box 11)
    - Committee on Oberly Memorial Fund 1922-1928 (Box 11)
    - Committee on preparation of a Bibliography of Humanistic Literature 1921-1922 (Box 11)
    - Committee on Printed Card Memorial 1925-1927 (Box 11)
    - Committee on Public Documents 1908, 1910 (Box 11)
    - Committee on Rag Stock Paper for Government Publications 1927-1928 (Box 11)
    - Committee on Recruiting 1927-1928 (Box 11)
    - Committee on Reorganization of the Catalog Section 1922-1923 (Box 11)
    - Committee on Library Resources 1922-1923 (Box 11)
    - Committee on Resources of American Libraries 1921-1927 (Box 11)
    - Committee on Resources 1935-1936 (Box 11)
    - Committee on Resources 1935-1945 (Box 12)
    - Committee on Rockefeller Memorial 1922-1924 (Box 12)
    - Committee on Sabin's Dictionary 1924-1925 (Box 12)
    - Committee on Salaries (Box 12)
    - Committee on Union List of Government Serials 1925-1926 (Box 12)
    - Committee on Salary of Librarian of Congress 1926-1927 (Box 12)
    - Commission on Library and Adult Education 1924-1925 (Box 12)
    - Commission on Library and Adult Education 1925/26-1928 (Box 13)
    - Conference of University Librarians 1919-1924 (Box 13)
    - Conference of Librarians of Large Public Libraries 1923-1924 (Box 13)
    - Conference of University and College Librarians 1928-1929 (Box 13)
    - Congressional Commission 1919 (Box 13)
    - Constitution 1919-1921 (Box 13)
    - Endowment Fund 1919 (Box 13)
    - European Representatives 1919-1920 (Box 13)
    - Friends of the Library 1935-1939 (Box 13)
    - German Periodicals 1921-1923 (Box 13)
    - Journal of discussion 1927-1929 (Box 13)
    - Leipzig Exhibit 1914 (Box 13)
    - Lending section 1923-1924 (Box 13)
    - Library Pioneers 1924-1925 (Box 13)
    - Panama-Pacific Exposition 1914-1915 (Box 13)
    - Paris Library 1920 (Box 13)
    - Publishing Board 1909-1925 (Box 13)
    - School Libraries Section 1920 (Box 13)
    - Survey 1919 (Box 13)
    - War-related
      - Library War Finance Committee 1919 (Box 13)
      - Library War Service Committee 1917-1919 (Box 13)
      - Committee on Aid to Libraries in War Areas 1942-1945 (Box 14)
- Carnegie Corporation of New York
  The series - Carnegie Corporation of New York - pertains to Bishop's professional relationship with this foundation and his participation on various of its advisory groups.
  - General files 1930-1941 (Box 14)
  - Advisory Group on College Libraries 1928-1929/30 (Box 14)
  - Advisory Group on College Libraries 1930/31-1941 (Box 15)
  - Miscellaneous files, dates vary (Box 15)
  - Advisory Group on College Libraries (Canada) 1930-1934 (Box 16)
  - Advisory Group on Junior College Libraries 1933-1937 (Box 16)
  - Advisory Group on Junior College Libraries 1937-1940 (Box 17)
  - Advisory Group on University Libraries 1938-1939 (Box 17)
  - Foreign Libraries:
    - Australia (Box 17)
    - New Zealand (Box 17)
    - Near East (Box 17)
      arranged by college
  - Advisory Group on Teachers College Libraries, 1937-1940 (Box 17)
  - Advisory Group on Technological Colleges, state colleges, and colleges for Negroes (Box 17)
  - Survey of University Libraries 1925-1928 (Box 17)
  - Advisory Group on the American Library Association 1930-1932 (Box 17)
  - Michigan Project A (Box 17)
  - Advisory Group on Library Fellowships 1928-1935 (Box 17)
  - Advisory Group on Library Scholarship Grants 1928-1933 (Box 17)
  - Advisory Group on Library School Grants 1933-1934 (Box 17)
  - Appraisal Committee 1933-1934 (Box 17)
  - Advisory Group on College Libraries
    - Grant files (Box 17)
      (arranged by college)
    - Grant files (Box 18)
    - Colleges not receiving grants (Box 18)
  - Carnegie Corporation of New York miscellaneous 1920-1930 (Box 18)
  - Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching 1923-1925 (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous Carnegie files (Box 18)
  - Carnegie Endowment for International Peace 1928-1936 (Box 18)
- Topical files
  Topical Files, arranged alphabetically, consist of correspondence and other papers relating to Bishop's other organizational and personal interests.
  - American Academy in Rome (Box 19)
  - American Book Center for Devastated Libraries (Box 19)
  - American Library in London (Box 19)
  - American Library in Paris 1945-1946 (Box 19)
  - Books for Latin America (Box 19)
  - Chicago University Graduate Library School 1926 (Box 19)
  - Commonwealth Fund 1924-1925 (Box 19)
  - Chrysostom Manuscripts 1922-1923 (Box 19)
  - Columbia University (Box 19)
  - Committee of Library Experts (Box 19)
  - Congress International Provisoire des Bibliothecaires (Box 19)
  - Cornell University (Box 19)
  - Cosmos Club 1915-1940 (Box 19)
  - Duodecimos 1926-1928 (Box 19)
  - Grosvenor Library 1917-1930 (Box 19)
  - Institute of International Education 1919-1925 (Box 19)
  - International Bibliography of Humanistic Studies 1919-1921 (Box 19)
  - International Congress of Librarians 1928-1929 (Box 19)
  - International Congress of Library Experts 1928-1929 (Box 19)
  - International Congresses 1922-1924 (Box 19)
  - International Federation of Library Associations 1929-1933/34 (Box 19)
  - International Federation of Library Associations 1934/35-1941 (Box 20)
  - International Institute of Bibliography 1918-1925 (Box 20)
  - International Institute of Intellectual Cooperation 1925-1933, 1945 (Box 20)
  - International Library Cooperation 1928-1929 (Box 20)
  - Institute of International Education (Box 20)
  - Joint Committee on Books for Devastated Libraries (Box 20)
  - League of Nations Library 1924-1930 (Box 20)
  - Library History 1927-1928 (Box 21)
  - Library Journal 1914-1925 (Box 21)
  - Library of Congress 1930-1931 (Box 21)
  - Library of Congress: Catalog of Printed Cards (Box 21)
  - Library Science (Dept.), University of Michigan (Box 21)
  - Lydenberg, H.M. 1922-1924 (Box 21)
  - Lomer, G.R. 1926-1934 (Box 21)
  - Mailing list (Box 21)
  - Mary Bloom Manny Memorial. Fund 1925-1926 (Box 21)
  - Miller, Wilhelm 1917 (Box 21)
  - Monroe County Library (Box 21)
  - Munthe, Wilhelm 1932-1939 (Box 21)
  - New International Encyclopedia 1916-1919 (Box 21)
  - New International Yearbook 1919-1921 (Box 21)
  - Our Lady of the Lake College (Box 21)
  - Pan American Bibliographical Congress (Box 21)
  - Paris Library School 1923-1932 (Box 21)
  - Paris Museum National Histoire Naturelle (Box 21)
  - Parsons, Mary P. 1928-1939 (Box 21)
  - Penniman, J.R. 1921 (Box 21)
  - Phi Beta Kappa 1913-1936 (Box 21)
  - "Poor Paper" Books (Box 21)
  - Prussian State Library 1925-1940 (Box 21)
  - Putnam Anniversary Volume 1928-1929 (Box 21)
  - Randall, William 1925-1935 (Box 21)
  - Reed, Katherine 1940-1941 (Box 21)
  - Research Club 1925-1935 (Box 21)
  - Rice Institute 1929-1941 (Box 21)
  - Richardson, E.C. 1926-1938 (Box 21)
  - Roland-Marcel 1930-1931 (Box 21)
  - Sending-Larsen, Holger 1932-1933 (Box 21)
  - Sumner, Edward A. 1928-1929 (Box 21)
  - Teachers college journals (Box 21)
  - Utley, George B (Box 21)
  - Van der Riet, F.G. 1945 (Box 21)
  - Vatican research (Box 21)
  - Vatican Norme 1937-1941 (Box 21)
  - Voynich, W.M. 1910-1920 (Box 21)
  - Voynich, W.M. 1920-1939 (Box 22)
  - War periodicals (Box 22)
  - Western College for Women 1929-1930 (Box 22)
  - Williams and Wilkins Co. 1915-1925 (Box 22)
  - Worcester County Law Library 1915-1937 (Box 22)
- Biographical/personal and miscellaneous
  The Biographical/personal and miscellaneous series consists of biographical information, files relating to the reunions and other alumni activities of the class of 1892 and 1893 of the University of Michigan, and Christmas cards from the period of 1929-1930 There are also three personal diaries dated 1912, 1913, and 1916.
  - Biographical miscellanea (Box 22)
  - Christmas Cards
    - 1929-1930, 2 folders (Box 22)
  - Citations (Box 22)
    (see also diplomas in oversize folder Ac)
  - Diaries 1912, 1913, 1916, 3 volumes (Box 22)
  - U. of M. Student miscellanea (Box 22)
  - U-M Class of 1892 alumni and reunion material (Box 22)
  - U-M Class of 1893 alumni and reunion materials (Box 22)
  - Printed materials, 3 folders (Box 23)
- Student Notebooks
  Student Notebooks date from 1890 to 1893 when Bishop was a student at the University of Michigan. This series is of most importance for the notes taken by Bishop on the philosophy lectures of John Dewey. Microfilm copies of these notes are available for inter-library loan.
  - University of Michigan student notebooks 1890-1893 (Box 23)
  - Notes and lectures on classical studies (Box 23)
  - University of Michigan student notebooks 1890-1893 (Box 24)
    (include notes on the philosophy lectures of John Dewey; microfilm copy of Dewey lectures also available)
- Photographs
  The Photographs include portraits, photographs of Bishop receiving awards or participating in various library functions and conventions. (The photographs series also includes oversize photos in Ac folder.)
  - Portraits of Bishop and his wife Finie Burton (Box 25)
  - Informal portraits and snapshots (Box 25)
  - Bishop receiving awards and attending various meetings of librarians (Box 25)
  - University of Michigan Library School classes 1918-1921 (Box 25)
  - William Clements Library dedication 1923 (Box 25)
  - Quadrangle Club circa 1930 (Box 25)
  - European conventions of librarians
    - Barcelona (Box 25)
    - Bern 1931-1934 (Box 25)
    - Madrid 1935 (Box 25)
    - Rome 1929 (Box 25)
  - Bishop with Monsignor Tisserant circa 1927-1928 (Box 25)
  - Monastery of St. John on Patmos 1920 (Box 25)
    (taken by Francis W. Kelsey)
  - Portraits of librarians (Box 25)